Let's try now to modify our solution
by taking down the no preemption case.
The idea behind what we are going to see next can
be summarized as follows: If a philosopher does
not manage to get the chopstick on the right,
then he/she releases the chopstick on the left.
This is how the solution looks like. Let's first
introduce some data structures and methods.
We define the type chopstick_structure
so that it contains a binary semaphore
initialized to 1 and a boolean variable
called available initialized to true
(which means that at the very beginning of the
execution each chopstick_structure is available).
We then define the trylock method so that,
when passed a chopstick_structure the first
thing it does is to wait on its binary semaphore.
After the wait, if the chopstick is available,
it sets the variable to false and
stores true as return value, otherwise
it stores false as return value. Finally,
it sends a signal on the chopstick's binary
semaphore and returns the return value.
The lock method simply enters a loop in
which it stays until trylock returns true (i.e.,
when it finds the chopstick to be available).
The release waits on the binary semaphore.
Then, it sets the available variable to true
and signals the binary semaphore.
We can now look at the solution as a whole.
In their entry section, the threads define
a while loop. The loop goes on as long as a local
variable called holding_both_chopsticks is false.
Inside the loop, the thread tries to lock the
first chopstick. Based on the method we have
introduced, it means it keeps running trylock as
longs as it does not find the available variable
of the chopstick it is trying to lock set to true.
After that, it runs trylock on the second
chopstick. If try lock returns true, then the
chopstick available variable was true, and
the thread sets holding_both_chopsticks to true,
exits the loop, and enters the critical section.
Otherwise, the thread
releases the other chopstick.
After the critical section, each
thread/philosopher runs release on both chopsticks
and sets holding_both_chopsticks to false.
Then, the thread/philosopher enters the
remainder section, in which he/she
can think instead of eating.
If you look at this solution carefully, you
can see a thread enters its critical section
only if both chopsticks are available and,
when a thread finds the first chopstick to
be availalbe but not the second one,
the first is set to available again,
which means in the next iteration of loop the
thread will try again to get both chopsticks.
This solution is valid when it comes to mutual
exclusion, and it also avoids deadlocks.
It has 2 downsides, still. One is that a process
can starve, since one process X could be the one
that is always managing to get both chopsticks.
The other downside is that, while preventing
deadlocks, this algorithm
does not prevent livelocks.
We have not discussed livelocks in details, but I
just want to draw your attention on the fact that
if there are two processes and if both processes
do not manage to get the second chopstick
it might happen that in some execution
order (imagine the two processes are
concurrently being executed on the same CPU) they
both release the other chopstick and try again,
and this try and retry can go on
for an unbounded number of times.